Hello everyone. Welcome to the annual
finance rewind here on the plane bagel.
I'm your host Richard Coffin. We have
made it to the end of yet another
eventful 12 months mostly in one piece.
And as is tradition here on the plane
bagel, we'll take the opportunity as we
adorn our festive sweaters to reflect
and take a walk down memory lane on the
key happenings and events that help
define 2025. I always quite enjoy doing
these videos. to give me a good chance
to reflect on everything and just
remember the stuff that maybe we uh
forgot really happened this year. As we
summarize some of the key events of the
year, we'll also take the opportunity to
discuss key trends going into 2026. So,
settle in, grab yourself a cozy drink
and sweater like myself. Uh we are here
to unwind after all with this rewind. I
know that might be difficult given the
past year we've had, but we'll do our
best to keep things light-hearted as we
uh take the opportunity to discuss the
year we've had. A quick thank you to
Brilliant for sponsoring this finance
rewind. Stick to the end for an
exclusive offer on their platform. And
without further ado, let's hop into it.
January 17th, Donald Trump launches
Salana based memecoin, Trumpcoin.
All right, bad start. I agree. But but
stick with me. We we can make it through
this. The cryptocurrency, which comes
just 3 days before Trump's inauguration
as president of the United States,
surges over a few days from just over a
dollar to nearly $75 a coin before
correcting downwards. The move
foreshadows a year of crypto friendly
policies from the White House and draws
some criticism from those who believe
that pumping a memecoin that you own 80%
of presents a conflict of interest for
the president of the United States.
Trump puts concerns to rest by offering
an exclusive dinner to top holders of
the memecoin. January 18th in briefly
the most important news in the finance
world. Tik Tok goes dark as a ban takes
effect in the United States. The app, of
course, comes back online the following
day as the government gives Bite Dance,
the Chinese parent company of Tik Tok,
75 days to find a US owner for its US
operations. The ban goes on to be
delayed a number of times throughout the
year with the US government balancing
the need to protect user data from
Chinese snooping with American
dependence on influencer advisers and
poorly researched stock picks. In
December, news comes out that the app
has finally entered a deal with an
investor group backed by the likes of
Oracle and Abu Dhabi based MGX. January
20th, Donald Trump is inaugurated as the
president of the United States and hits
the ground running, issuing a record
number of executive orders on his first
day in office, and keeping up the
blistering pace throughout his first
year. A number of the president's orders
prove quite controversial, including an
attempt to end birthright citizenship,
the weakening of regulatory agencies
like the SEC and FTC, the ending of DEI
programs within the government, a move
that's mirrored by many corporations in
the country, the detention and
deportation of immigrants, both illegal
and legal, the gutting and shuttering of
US institutions like US Aid and
Department of Education, the sending of
the National Guard to quell dangerous
protesters in quote, "war ravaged
Portland, and of course, making showers
great again by ending the left's war on
water pressure, one of the eight such
wars the president would help end in his
first year. January 20th is also the day
Donald Trump establishes Doge or the
Department of Government Efficiency to
cut back on government excess headed by
penny pincher extraordinaire Elon Musk
who promptly asks workers what they did
last week. The initiative follows a
pledge by Elon Musk to cut $2 trillion
from government spending and comes with
a website where the group transparently
posts really big numbers that they've
potentially saved. Shockingly, reports
soon follow that hiring a group of
inexperienced college students and
recent grads to override billions of
dollars of government contracts may not
have been a good idea with analyses
pointing to grossly exaggerated figures
and government spending actually going
on to increase slightly for the year.
The group dispands in November with 8
months left in its charter. February
1st, in the first of the many exhausting
tariff updates to come in the year,
Donald Trump signs an executive order
slapping 10% tariffs on Chinese goods
and 25% tariffs on Canadian and Mexican
goods. Tariffs that, while initially
delayed for the latter two countries,
ultimately go into effect in March. The
president cites fentanyl and illegal
immigration as the main reasons behind
these tariffs despite Canada in
particular representing a small fraction
of both issues. The levies are followed
by additional sector specific tariffs
targeting auto parts, steel and
aluminum, copper parts, lumber and
furniture, key industries for the three
trade partners. Canada and China
retaliate with tariffs of their own.
April 2nd, we of course have the very
fateful liberation day where Donald
Trump shows off some very fancy bristle
board posters and liberates the world
from free trade, introducing a 10%
baseline tariff on all imports into the
country and a slew of higher country
specific tariffs calculated entirely off
of each country's trade balance with the
United States. Markets dropped 12% over
just a week before the punitive tariffs
are postponed to allow time for
negotiation with the US ultimately
entering arrangements with the UK,
Japan, and the entirety of the EU among
other countries throughout the year.
Higher tariffs come back into effect for
most other nations. August 1st, April
4th, just 2 days after Liberation Day,
China slaps a 34% tariff on US goods in
response to the now 54% tariff faced by
Chinese goods. With the country also
introducing export restrictions on key
rare earth metals required for the
production of certain high-tech
products. And like an UNO pickup 4chain
gone terribly wrong, things escalate
quickly. The US hikes its own tariffs by
50%. China calls and goes up 50% as
well. The US jumps right to 145% at the
same time it postpones liberation day
tariffs for all other countries. China
hikes its total to 125%. And then on May
12th, everything's walked back as both
countries settle on a 10% baseline
tariff. Tensions cool further on
November 4th as the countries announce
an agreement to ease trade restrictions
further for a year. April 28th, we
return to Canada where Mark Carney is
elected the next prime minister of the
country in a surprising turn of fortune
for the Liberal Party. The former Bank
of Canada and Bank of England governor
goes on to take a fairly centrist
position, opting to invest heavily in
promoting so-called nation building
projects while axing the country's
consumer carbon tax, reducing the public
employee headcount, and tightening
immigration. While the PM loses contact
with Trump over offensive claims made in
an ad by Ronald Reagan that tariffs
don't work, Canada strangely finds
itself in an advantage position with its
flat 35% tariff. With 85% of its goods
sent to the US still being tariff-free
due to an exemption for goods compliant
with its free trade agreement that's
still being honored by the US. With the
agreement coming due for review in 2026,
however, challenges remain for the
Canadian PM. May 3rd, after over 60
years as CEO, Warren Buffett announces
his retirement at the annual Bergkshire
Hathaway shareholder meeting in Omaha,
Nebraska. I attend the meeting but
missed the announcement by a couple
minutes, waiting in line for some peanut
brittle. Buffett helped grow Bergkshire
Hathway from a failing textile
manufacturer into one of the largest
conglomerates in the world worth over $1
trillion, being viewed by many as one of
the greatest investors of our time.
While Bergkshire stock falls on the
announcement over concerns of whether
anyone can match Buffett's leadership,
Warren hands the reigns over to someone
he believes is able. Greg Ael, that is.
July 4th, Donald Trump signs the one big
beautiful bill into law, initiating
trillions of dollars in tax breaks and
spending cuts, most notably to social
aid programs like SNAP, food benefits,
and Medicaid. Despite the government
expected to save $1.1 trillion from
direct spending cuts and GDP growth
expected to be 2 percentage points
higher thanks to the budget, the
government deficit is ultimately
expected to increase by 3 to4 trillion
over the next decade due to the lower
revenue and higher spending in certain
categories with the bill sending funds
to enhance ICE operations and to
construct a Golden Dome missile defense
system over the United States. The
budget also includes a tax advantaged
account for American children and
initially included a so-called revenge
tax imposing a levy on investment income
earned by foreign investors, though that
section was later removed. July 18th,
during the so-called crypto week, we see
lawmakers pass the Genius Act, the first
major national piece of legislation
targeting cryptocurrencies in the United
States. The law sets up a regulatory
regime for stable coins or
cryptocurrencies that peg their value to
that of the US dollar, imposing
disclosure, redemption, and registration
requirements onto stable coin issuers,
and moving oversight of the industry
away from the SEC and CFTC, defining
stable coins as neither a security nor a
commodity. The other two pieces of
cryptoeek legislation, the Clarity Act
and AntiCBDC Act, failed to pass the
finish line. August 22nd, Federal
Reserve Chair Jerome Powell delivers his
Jackson Hole remarks at the Fed's annual
symposium, where as part of a five-year
review, he announces a return of the
central bank to a flexible inflation
targeting regime and a balanced approach
regarding its dual mandate of maximum
employment and stable prices. The speech
follows months of criticism and even an
attempted firing of Powell by the
president over the bank's high interest
rates, but signals the bank's
willingness to loosen restrictive policy
amid a weakening labor market. The
central bank ultimately cuts rates three
times after the speech and ends its
quantitative tightening program December
1st. September 22nd, Nvidia announces
that it will invest $100 billion into
OpenAI to support its buildout of data
centers in return for OpenAI filling
those data centers with Nvidia chips, a
deal that some come to label as
circular. The move raises concerns over
the propping up of the supposed AI
bubble characterized by blistering
infrastructure buildout, high stock
valuations, and absurdly large
partnerships from unprofitable companies
with OpenAI, the company behind Sora and
ChachiBT itself entering deals to spend
$1.4 trillion over the next 8 years
despite earning less than 2% of that as
revenue. While the technology continues
to advance, offering exceedingly
impressive output, concerns remain over
whether enduser demand will justify the
billions of dollars of investment and
investor hype. With even the government
getting in on the action with an
investment in Intel, Nvidia, the
chipmaker at the center of most of these
incestuous AI partnerships, becomes the
first company to reach a $5 trillion
valuation in October. October 1st, we
enter the longest government shutdown in
US history as the Senate fails to pass
appropriations legislation with
Democratic lawmakers pushing to extend
affordable care act subsidies left to
expire under the one big beautiful bill.
The shutdown lasts 43 days, disrupting
the collection of CPI and labor data for
the month of October and ultimately ends
November 12th when Republicans agree to
put the matter to a vote in December. As
of recording, the issue remains
outstanding, but with no government
shutdown to threaten, it appears that
the subsidies will expire by year end.
October 6th, Bitcoin reaches a new
all-time high of over $126,000
per coin, up 30% for the year before
correcting downwards and ultimately
ending the year down in the mid-s
singledigit range. While 2025 would be a
year full of catalysts for the
cryptocurrency, including political
endorsements, the establishment of US
Bitcoin strategic reserve in March, the
pardoning of crypto Silk Road founder
Ross Albrech, and the rise of Bitcoin
Treasury companies who raise capital
solely for the purpose of buying
Bitcoin, and funding Michael Sailor's
midjourney subscriptions. The correction
ultimately reflects lower liquidity in
the financial system and heightened
investor concerns over the asset, which
has come to act more like a volatile
tech stock than the promised safe haven
that many purported to be. October 7th,
we see ICE Inc., the owner of the New
York Stock Exchange, invest $2 billion
in Poly Market, a crypto-based betting
platform. The move reflects the growing
integration of so-called prediction
markets like Poly Market and Kalshi
where users bet on the outcome of
literally anything into the financial
system with apps like Robin Hood and
Coinbase even announcing moves to
integrate prediction markets right
alongside investor portfolios, enabling
users to lose their money gambling in
addition to losing it on call options
and crypto. Despite sports betting being
banned in a number of states, the apps
have so far managed to circumvent
gambling laws by successfully arguing
that betting on the existence of aliens
in 2025 is actually a prudent investment
strategy, I guess, and should be
regulated at the federal level. It
remains to be seen whether the argument
holds up to challenges and whether we in
fact see aliens confirmed by year end.
October 28th, Startup 1X launches
pre-orders for its humanoid helper
robot, Neo, the first consumerready
robot in the race to build machines
capable of replacing humans in the
performance of broad menial tasks. While
intended to eventually run autonomously,
Neo robots will for now be controlled by
a dedicated operator until they
eventually figure out the whole AI part.
The development is a blow to Elon Musk,
who's already duking things out with Sam
Alman over Chachib being too woke and
now has to deal with Optimus being
dethroned as the leading autonomous
human operated robot. But hey, at least
he finally got his robo taxis this year.
December 19th, the Bank of Japan hikes
its central bank target rate to 75%, the
highest level since 1995. A move that
comes at a time where the country faces
all-time high yields for its government
bonds. The country, one of the only
developed nations currently hiking
interest rates, faces rising inflation
and aggressive stimulus measures from
its newly elected prime minister, Sai
Dai, aimed at improving the country's
lagging GDP growth. The higher rates
come at the same time as jitters in the
US bond market, which has likewise seen
its bond yields rise on weak demand
despite the country seeing falling
interest rates, and has overall raised
concerns over another Japanese carry
trade unwinding, an event that in 2024
led traders to sell off US assets to pay
back borrowed yen. And then finally on
December 21st, after previously reaching
a new all-time high in October, gold
hits another record price and continues
pushing upward, reaching as of Friday a
price of over $4,500 per troy ounce.
With the precious metal jumping over 70%
year-to date amid accumulation by
central banks, institutions, and a mania
of buying activity from retail investors
in both physical and ETF markets. Silver
likewise sees its own price reach a new
all-time high, rising over 100% over the
course of 2025. While some dubbed the
rally as the great debasement trade,
reflecting market concerns over the US
dollar, other analysts instead described
the move as investor FOMO, marking a
strange change of characteristic for the
asset, which historically has been
treated more as a safe haven rather than
something investors plow into when
markets themselves are at all-time
highs. And that concludes our rewind of
2025. Before hopping into the trends of
2026, if you're one for New Year's
resolutions and keen to learn something
new or just interested in cementing your
understanding of uh something that maybe
just never clicked for you, then you
should check out the sponsor of today's
video, Brilliant, an offering that can
help hone your math, problem solving,
and other skills in the new year.
Brilliant offers a learning platform for
topics ranging from data and math to
programming and AI using interactive
exercises to let you play around with
the concepts that you're learning, which
is really what makes the offering
unique. Brilliant focuses on a method
called active learning, which has been
shown by research to be a more effective
way of learning than just listening to
lectures or watching videos online. And
with practice that's being personalized
to your level of understanding, it can
really help you take your learning to
that next level. Their exploring data
visually is a really great one because
it's where their interactive activities
really shine. Offering a much more
intuitive way of learning concepts that
otherwise can be hard to visualize. So
to learn more about Brilliant and try
them for 30 days free, you can visit
brilliant.org/theplaybagle
/theplanebagel or scan the QR code on
screen. Viewers will also get 20% off an
annual premium subscription for
unlimited daily access to everything on
Brilliant. So, thank you Brilliant for
sponsoring this Finance Rewind. And as
we look into 2026 and the trends that
we're experiencing moving into that
year, much like how many people have
described the economy as having this
sort of K-shaped growth with the top
percent experiencing a very different
set of outcomes from the bottom percent,
we have a very bifurcated outlook. On
the one hand, there is some optimism in
the space. The US economy has continued
to see strong growth in spite of
tariffs. The stock market has had a
stellar year thanks to big tech. And
with AI developing at breakneck speed,
some hold the view that the technology
will revolutionize and improve
everything we do from the emails we
write, the programs we code, even the
content we create. On the other hand,
there's a whole lot of uncertainty.
There's the concern that the AI bubble
is propping up the economy with 40% of
GDP growth in the US coming from the
tech buildout and 10 companies in the
S&P 500 now making up roughly 40% of the
index. There's a concern that inflation
currently above target will continue to
increase unabated with a new Trump
appointed Federal Reserve chair set to
take the position in 2026. There's the
concern that the K-shaped economy is
much weaker than the general print
figures would lead you to believe with
tariffs continuing to disrupt certain
sectors, manufacturing contracting, and
the labor market showing signs of
weakness. And of course, there's a
concern that heightened geopolitical
tensions will continue to intensify with
2025 marking a stark increase in direct
military interventions from the US in
Yemen, Iran, and of course, Venezuela,
where the US has been bombing civilian
boats accused of smuggling drugs and
intercepting oil tankers in a major
escalation for the country. And while we
did see a ceasefire announced in Gaza
and ceasefire talks between Russia and
Ukraine, there's little confidence we'll
actually see peace hold out with strikes
continuing in Gaza and Ukraine and
Russia still far apart regarding
ceasefire terms. In addition to the
actual war, we'll of course continue to
see the trade war develop in the new
year as global economies continue to
negotiate and adapt to US tariffs and
legal challenges play out in the courts.
We can also expect further deregulation
in 2026 under the Trump administration.
And we'll have to see how prediction
markets fare given the scrambling of
companies to enter and build out the
space and stakeholders preparing for the
legal challenges to come. Of course,
likely the biggest investment theme
going into 2026 is none other than the
AI bubble, which will likely continue to
remain top of mind as the massive
buildout continues. But with Trump's
track record of giving markets whiplash
with his unprecedented and questionable
policies and lastminute changes to said
policies, it's anyone's guess what
themes will dominate the markets and how
2026 will ultimately shake out. Here's
hoping it ends up being a bit more
plain. But that is our finance rewind
for 2025. There were of course many
other notable events that happened
throughout the year. the wildfires in
LA, the new pope from Chicago, the
election to Mum Donnie in New York, the
murder of Charlie Kirk, and the
transparent release of some Epstein
files by accident. But hopefully this
video offered a helpful review and
summary of the key headlines and events
of 2025, and hopefully more engaging
than if you had just asked Chad to do it
for you. And one final point before I
sign off for the rest of 2025, I want to
once again thank you all for watching,
subscribing, and overall supporting the
plane bagel this past 12 months. Uh 2025
was the year that we passed 1 million
subscribers here on the plane dagel. I
got the shiny gold play button. So,
thank you so much for for affording me
that and the other opportunities that
have come with this. I've gotten to
launch a new podcast with my co-orker
Derek Deadman, the dead on the money
personal finance podcast. I've gotten to
sit on panels and talk about topics I'm
passionate about, to meet and
collaborate with other creators. I
recently got to interview with YouTube
OG Philip DeFranco. I even got
impersonated by an AI scammer this year,
which you know, I'm not thankful for
that, but it does feel like a milestone.
So, you know, still weirdly proud of it.
But genuinely, it's been an incredible
time in spite of the ridiculous nature
of some of the stories we cover. And
2026 is shaping up to be another great
year for the channel. So, thank you. I
hope in these crazy times you find the
time to relax, unwind, and look forward
to the new year. I'll be here posting
about the finance stuff in 2026, and I
look forward to seeing you there. So,
happy holidays, merry Christmas, happy
new year.